All right, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף Daf is ד Daled
and we pick up towards the bottom of ג עמוד ב. Gimmel
Amud Bet. We're dealing with a ברייתא, Braita, it's actually a תוספתא
Tosefta more or less, that says about this מנהג minhag of getting
married on Wednesday, that when there was an אונס, ones, they, excuse
me, when there was a סכנה, sakana, the p- they started getting
married on Tuesday, which the גמרא Gemara defines to mean that somebody
the the the governor, the local ruler, basically forced the women to
have sex with him on their wedding night and if not presumably
their lives were at stake so obviously they wanted to make it
less obvious which day they were getting married. And then it says
that if it's a time of אונס ones then they can get
married also on another day, and it gave the example of Monday.
So let's pick up from there. ובשני לא יכנוס, U'vishaini Lo Yichnos,
don't generally get married on Mondays. ואם מחמת האונס, Ve'im Machmas Ha-ones,
about ten lines from the bottom, line starts with the word ואם
מחמת, Ve'im Machmas, ואם מחמת האונס מותר, Ve'im Machmas Ha-ones Mutar, and
if it's because of some אונס, ones, which is not a risk
of life, that's סכנה, sakana, but other some type of event out
of somebody's control that makes it impossible, then it's permissible. Okay, so
what's the אונס, ones, right? Because you have to know you have
to be able to anticipate it, because you're doing it early. All
right, or you're not postponing it to the next Wednesday. So there's
something about that coming Wednesday. So מאי אונס? Mai Ones? So what
is that? מאי אונס אילימא הך דאמרן, Mai Ones Ileima Hada Amrin,
if it's like we were talking about before, that this p- the
you know governor had to have sex with the bride on their
wedding night and it's an אונס ones because he's forcing them to
have sex, so and it's saying that if you had to do
it on a Monday, not just on a Tuesday you can do
it on a Monday also. התם קרי ליה סכנה והכא קרי ליה
אונס, Hasam Karei Lei Sakana Ve-hacha Karei Lei Ones, why are you
switching the terms? First you were calling it a סכנה sakana because
it was a risk of life and now you're calling it an
אונס? ones? So it seems like we're talking about something different, not
about the same thing. ותו התם נהגו הכא מותר, Ve-su Hasam Nahagu
Hacha Mutar, also there it says that the practice like you know
developed to do it on a different day, and here it says
that it is permissible which sounds like somehow that it's an explicit
like ruling of the sages or sounds like it's a לכתחילה. l'chatchila.
Of course one would think that it's a לכתחילה l'chatchila there too
if you're doing it to avoid getting raped or having your life
at stake. But anyway, it certainly seems to frame it in a
different way. רשי Rashi says that מותר mutar maybe sounds not just
a difference of לכתחילה בדיעבד l'chatchila b'diavad but sounds like it is
a preferred individual as opposed to a communal issue. אמר רבא דאמרי
שר צבא בא לעיר, Amar Rava De'amri Sar Tzava Ba L'ir, so
it's a very a much more mundane type of an אונס. ones.
They say that the g- the the general, the colonel is coming
to the city with his army troops, and of course they're going
to requisition all of the food in the city and whatever they
find. So you don't want to be spending all your money for
the wedding feast on the day that the troops are coming and
going to requisition all the food. So you want to have it
earlier. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says היכי דמי, Heichi Dami, what's
the case? אי דאתי וחליף, I De-ati Ve-chalif, if he's going to
be there and leave and pass through, לעכב, le'akev, so then just
wait. Now what does just wait mean? רשי Rashi says it means
if he's going to leave like in a few days just wait
till the next Wednesday. That's what רשי Rashi says. תוספות Tosfos says
תוספות Tosfos doesn't like that. So תוספות Tosfos says one minute... ואי
משתכב
כל יום ד אין לו לעכב
עד עד הערייא. Ve-i Misakev
Kol Yom Dalet Ain Lo Le'akev
Ad Ad Ha-araiah. ולא חליף בגדול גופיה... Ve-lo Chalif Bi-gdol Gufei...
Yeah,
I don't really understand תוספות's Tosfos read. תוספות's Tosfos read is is
that if he's leaving on that same Wednesday, just have the p-
just have the party after Wednesday. You know, just have the party
later on Wednesday. But that really doesn't make any sense because the
problem of אונס ones is that once you've gathered up all the
food he's going to seize all the food. So we'll read it
רשי's Rashi way. Okay, if he's going to be leaving after a
short period of time, you know, just postpone the wedding for a
week but do it next Wednesday or in two Wednesdays. So the
גמרא Gemara says no, לא צריכא דאתי וקבע. Lo Tzricha De-ati Ve-kava.
Okay, he's going to be there for an indefinite amount of time.
So if he's going to be settling in and going to be
there for an indefinite amount of time you can't do it later
on a Wednesday, you gotta do it early. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says so בג מי יכנוס, Be-gimmel Mi Yichnos, so if he's
coming on a Wednesday so get married on a Tuesday which is
such a funny question, why didn't it say he's coming on a
Tuesday?
But you know once it says that he's going to be there
for a while say he's coming on a Tuesday so you have
to do on a Monday. But maybe there's some like then there's
no חידוש, chiddush, right? Then of course so there's got to be
some חידוש chiddush that the event is hap- the problem's happening on
Wednesday and we're letting you do it on Monday. So what's the
case?
So they said אספרווא דידיה, Asaf Rava Didei, which is like his
you know his like troops or his like advanced retinue, his
advanced you
know בג קא אתו Be-gimmel Ka Atu was gonna come on Tuesday.
So you know he's coming on Wednesday so but we're going to
say you can even go ahead and do it on Monday, you
can do it however early you need to do it to avoid
all of the food being seized. Okay,
so that's one answer, very like whatever certain mundane thing that requires
you to have the feast early so you don't have all the
food seized.
Can you also say it's like one of these things, you know,
it's not human, like a, you know, expect a really bad storm,
like does that fall into that category?
Well, but then we might say wait a week, you know, wait
until the next one.
Well then the roads will be bad.
Alright, so that might be, might be parallel. ואי בעית אימא ve'ee
ba'is eima now we get to something more interesting halakhically. If you
want you could say here's the אונס. ones. מה מחמת אונס, mai
machmas ones, כדתניא kidtanya like we have a ברייתא braita and this
is, you know, and this is clearly an issue that comes up,
you know, that the ברייתות braisos deal with and this is what
we're going to spend the rest of the day dealing with is
this particular scenario. So whether it's what אונס ones meant in the
first ברייתא braita or not, it certainly is a special case that
is dealt with in terms of the wedding night that, you know,
a number of ברייתות braisos deal with that we're going to focus
on. And here's the case, כדתניא. kidtanya. הרי שהיה פתו אפוי harei
shehaya pito afui וטבחו טבוח. utivcho tavuach.
You're all ready for the wedding feast. You've got the bread baked,
fresh bread. You've got the meat slaughtered, fresh meat, which is obviously
very important in a time of refrigeration. ויינו מזוג, veyaino mazug, the
wine is mixed, everything's like basically ready to be eaten. If you
don't eat it right now it's going to be a lot worse.
Okay. ומת אביו של חתן או אמה של כלה, umais aviv shel
choson o imah shel kallah, and the father of the חתן chosson
or the mother of the כלה kallah died right before the wedding.
So what do you do? So there's one question which is, you
know, a close relative dies, a parent dies, I don't know, three
days before the wedding, right? So what are the הלכות halakhos about
אבילות avelus and do you go ahead with the wedding and the
חתן chosson and כלה kallah are in אבילות avelus and so on?
Here's a case where it's, I mean it's similar, but it's ממש
mamosh the day before and it's ממש mamosh to see there's a
way to also deal with the problem because they just died and
you just have to postpone the burial. There's an opportunity right, the
types of practical questions you generally get, the practical questions you tend
to get nowadays is that, you know, the person died and they
were buried and the person is within שבעה shiv'ah and it's the
wedding. Okay. But the special case, and that's part of this, I
mean because part of the question is going to be here once
the burial takes place and the person is in שבעה shiv'ah what
are the implications. But what makes this a particularly special case in
addition to the fact that like you know all of the great,
all of the tremendous financial loss you'll have is that the body
hasn't been buried yet. So you can manipulate the question about when
the אבילות avelus begins because the אבילות avelus doesn't begin until the
body is buried. So that is going to translate into a particular
leniency here. So let's take a look. So what do you do?
When you say
אונס, ones, suppose it's this? Alright, fine, we'll worry about it. Let's
take a look. So what do you do?
Does it not say also the mother of the groom?
We'll get to that too.
All
right, everybody, all questions will be answered. Everything comes to he who
waits. Okay. מכניסין את המת לחדר machnisin es hamais lachader ואת החתן
ואת הכלה לחופה. ve'es hachoson ve'es hakallah lachuppah. You put the corpse
into a room, you bring the חתן chosson and the כלה kallah
to a חופה. chuppah. Very like visual, like you know, this guy
goes there, they go there, they go into the חופה. chuppah. Okay.
So you basically have the wedding before the אבילות avelus has begun,
before the מת mais has been buried, while they're still אוננים. onanim.
Okay. So what's an interesting question: would they make ברכת אירוסין? Birkas
Erusin? Right, you're not supposed to like, you know, you're not making
ברכות brachos although you don't have to make ברכת אירוסין, Birkas Erusin,
you already did קידושין, kiddushin, I guess that makes it easier and
the שבע ברכות Sheva Brachos are made by the ציבור. tzibbur. Okay.
What
חופה chuppah here seems to mean is חדר. heder. Not necessarily.
I mean exactly what?
Yeah, I understand. I understand. Okay, so one minute. Okay, yeah, but
all right, we'll worry about exactly what חופה chuppah means later. But
maybe it means a special like a ייחוד yichud room, maybe it
means a symbolic חופה chuppah like we have, we'll talk about that.
ובועל בעילת מצווה ופורש. uvau bilas mitzvah uforsh. So you have the
נישואין nissuin and then they go and they have sex, okay? I
think what Rabbi Dov was assuming was it meant that they do
that under the חופה. chuppah. I'm not sure it means that. It
might mean that. If חופה chuppah means like a ייחוד yichud room
then it would mean that. Right, then it would mean that. But
it might just mean they go to the חופה chuppah and then
afterwards they have sex for the first time. ופורש uforsh and then
they separate. ונוהג שבעת ימי המשתה, venohag shivas yemei hamishteh, they have
the week of the wedding. ואחר כך נוהג שבעת ימי אבילות, ve'achar
kach nohag shivas yemei avelus, and then they have the week of
אבילות. avelus. So what is the point of this? The point of
this is, right, there's two questions here. One is like can they
have the wedding once they're, you know, if they're an אבל? avel?
Can
somebody have a wedding? I know, but I'm saying why did they
want to make it to wait for the אבילות avelus to take
place? So if the אבילות avelus had already taken place then the
question asked is can you have this נישואין? nissuin? Because נישואין nissuin
as opposed to קידושין, kiddushin, that's what's associated with שמחות simchas as
we see by the שבע ברכות Sheva Brachos and so on. So
number one is like קידושין kiddushin you could be an אבל, avel,
you could do קידושין kiddushin on תשעה באב, Tisha B'av, you know
on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, whatever. But can you have נישואין nissuin
for an אבל? avel? That's one question. And then can you have
sex as an אבל? avel? That's question number two. So those are
obviously reasons why you wouldn't want the אבילות avelus to have started
yet. But an additional reason is implicit here because even if for
some reason we would have allowed
But then as soon as the wedding was over, the נישואין nisuin
was over, then you would go back to normal אבילות, aveilus, right?
Where here, because the אבילות aveilus hasn't taken place yet, because they're
still אוננים, onanim, and you do the wedding first, their status as
the שבעת ימי המשתה shivas yimei hamishteh of the wedding of חתן
וכלה chosson v'kallah precedes their status of being
an whoever status of being an אבל. avel. And therefore what happens
is that the אבילות aveilus does not really kick in, right, until
the after the שבעת ימי המשתה shivas yimei hamishteh are done. Okay,
so what that allows you is not just thank you the wedding
night, but what
it also at not just to have the חופה chuppah and to
have the wedding night and to have sex that night, but what
it also allows you is to have the whole שבעת ימי המשתה
shivas yimei hamishteh and to say that the אבילות aveilus doesn't really
take place. It is like the case you haven't you bury after
the wedding night. So it's basically like the case of burying a
body during the רגל, regel, right, as opposed to because the week
of the שבעת ימי המשתה shivas yimei hamishteh of the חתן וכלה
chosson v'kallah is like a רגל, regel, right? So therefore you bury
before the רגל, regel, the אבילות aveilus began and okay you're not
נוהג noheig it on the רגל, regel, but at least the אבילות
aveilus already began. So here though, it's like burying it on the
רגל. regel. So there's a couple of things that we have managed
to do, right? We have managed to allow them to have the
קידושין, kidushin, the נישואין, nisuin, we've allowed them to have sex, we've
allowed them to go ahead and have the שבעת ימי המשתה shivas
yimei hamishteh first and then they're going to have the שבעת ימי
אבילות shivas yimei aveilus אחר כך נוהג שבעת ימי אבילות. achar kach
noheig shivas yimei aveilus. But כל אותן הימים, kol osan hayamim, now
during that week although the status of ימי המשתה yimei hamishteh רגל
regel as it were kicked in first and then you buried after
the חופה, chuppah, nevertheless the principle as we're going to say is
that דברים שבצנעה d'varim she'bitzina are נוהג. noheig. That even when you
know even when אבילות aveilus takes even when somebody dies during the
רגל regel and there's a burial like on חול המועד chol hamoed
or whatever, even though most of the visible forms of אבילות aveilus
don't take place, the private forms still do and that means that
there's still an איסור issur of having sex. Okay, so that's not
דברים שבצנעה. d'varim she'bitzina. Let's not worry right now about exactly listing
all the דברים שבצנעה, d'varim she'bitzina, but certainly the most classic example
of דברים שבצנעה d'varim she'bitzina which is not visible to anybody else
is the issue about marital relations, is the issue about sex. So
although there the רגל regel as it were began first, the שבעת
ימי המשתה shivas yimei hamishteh began first and then the אבילות aveilus
began, okay, the איסורים issurim of sex still apply, so what we
so therefore even though we allowed the first act of sex, we
are going to say for the rest of the week even during
the שבעת ימי המשתה, shivas yimei hamishteh, they cannot continue to have
sex. Okay, so therefore what are they going to do during that
time? So וכל אותן הימים הוא ישן בין האנשים והיא ישנה בין
הנשים. vechol osan hayamim hu yashen bein ha'anashim vehi yeshenah bein hanashim.
They have to sleep separate and they have to sleep in a
room he has to sleep in a room with other men and
she in a room with other women to prevent them from not
just that they're not ייחוד, yichud, but prevent them from actually getting
together because obviously you know there's a strong יצר הרע yeitzer hara
to get together, they just got married and so on. So the
גמרא Gemara is going to discuss why we're so מחמיר machmir about
this? By a normal married couple after they've had sex and the
woman is a נידה niddah for example, obviously they continue to sleep
in the same room. The answer the גמרא Gemara is going to
give is that since we were so lenient to do this manipulation,
right, to to make it so that the אבילות aveilus didn't have
to start and we allowed you first do your wedding or whatever,
you might not take the אבילות aveilus so seriously. And now anyway,
the אבילות aveilus hasn't really begun yet, it really begins in full
force after the רגל, regel, after your שבעת ימי המשתה. shivas yimei
hamishteh. Now it's only begun in a very private hidden way in
דברים שבצנעה. d'varim she'bitzina. So in this particular circumstance, you might not
be taking it so seriously and therefore we have to make a
double protection and make sure you're sleeping separate. Okay, one minute let's
just get this done. ואין מונעין תכשיטין מן הכלה כל שלושים יום
v'ein monin tachshitin min hakallah kol shloshim yom even though the אבילות
aveilus will begin certainly after the week and דברים שבצנעה d'varim she'bitzina
even during the week and so for the first thirty days normally
somebody's an אבל avel there's an issue about like getting a haircut
and other types of things about like beautifying their appearance. Nevertheless, and
so normally you'd let's say would not allow somebody to go ahead
and get like a makeover you know in during the שלושים, shloshim,
not going to talk about the specific הלכות אבילות hilchos aveilus but
certainly to do something to beautify themselves. Nevertheless, you do not prevent
the כלה kallah from doing that even if she's an אבילה aveilah
because this is the first month of marriage and you want to
do everything to like encourage you know attraction between the couple during
this month. ודווקא אביו של חתן או אמה של כלה. v'davka aviv
shel chosson o immah shel kallah. Here's your answer David, only the
father of the חתן chosson or the mother of the כלה, kallah,
not the reverse. Why not? דאיכא איניש דטרח להו d'ika inish d'tarach
lehu because the assumption is that these are the people that are
helping you get ready for the wedding. Okay, the כלה's kallah mother
would help her gather her trousseau and prepare her you know whatever,
the חתן's chosson father would, and therefore the sense is that if
we were to postpone it and just say oh well just do
it just do it like a week from now a month from
now when you're out of אבילות aveilus and so on, it's not
going to be the same because they would not have been as
prepared. Right now the mother did live to prepare her for... Prepare
her, the father would, and the חתן choson's father would, and therefore
the sense is that if we were to postpone it and just
say, "Oh, well, we'll just do it like a week from now,
a month from now, when you're out of אבילות aveilus and so
on," it's not going to be the same because they would not
have been as prepared. Right now, the mother did live to prepare
her for it, and then she died a minute before it took
place, so emotionally it might be very difficult, but at least she's
prepared for the wedding. If we wait a month, then the mother
won't be there to get her in the same to prepare her
to the same degree, and the same for him. So therefore that's
why we say we really have to do it now, we can't
just postpone it. Okay, אבל איפכא לא, aval ipcha lo, not the
opposite. So I'm just going to read some of these details about
like what's considered a case that we have to do it and
then we're going to go back and look at the halachic, you
know, חידושים chiddushim of what we all just said. So let's just
read a little more to like ground this. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this: אמר רב פפא בר פפא אמר רב חסדא, Amar
Rav Pappa bar Pappa Amar Rav Chisda, לא שנו אלא שנתן מים
אגבי בשר, lo shanu ela shenatan mayim agabi basar, אבל לא נתן
מים אגבי בשר, aval lo natan mayim agabi basar, מזדבן. mizdaben.
All of this is also when the meat has been rinsed, okay,
and therefore if you don't have the סעודה seuda now, you're not
going to be able to sell it because it's all going to
spoil if you don't eat it. But if it hasn't happened and
maybe it's still, it sounded like it was freshly שחט, shachted, so
but I don't know, it speaks about rinsing it and salt it
because you were getting out the blood. Anyway, if it hasn't been
rinsed and it's somewhat salted and preserved, then you won't have to
waste the food, you can just sell it. So therefore we don't
allow this. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, ובכרך, uvakrach, אף על פי שנתן
מים אגבי בשר, af al pi shenatan mayim agabi basar, מזדבן. mizdaben.
In a big city, even if it's been rinsed, you can go
ahead, you know, there's enough people that you can sell it, somebody
will buy it that day, it's not a problem. You go ahead
and you open up a stand, it'll all be gone in a
few hours. So then you would have to postpone the wedding because
you can just you can recoup your expenses. There's no big financial
loss. אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Pappa, ורב פפא אומר, veRav Pappa
omer, ובכפר, uvichfar, אף על פי שלא נתן מים אגבי בשר, af
al pi shelo natan mayim agabi basar, לא מזדבן. lo mizdaben. In
a village,
even if you haven't rinsed it, there aren't enough people to sell
all of the food. So if that's true, if a village you'll
never be able to sell and therefore it'll always be a loss,
and in a city you'll always be able to sell and never
be a loss, what was the case where it mattered whether you
had rinsed the meat or not? So exactly, that's what the גמרא
Gemara says. ואלא דרב חסדא היכי משכחת לה? ve'ela deRav Chisda heichi
meshkachat la? How do you get רב חסדא's Rav Chisda case? אמר
רב אשי
כגון מתא מחסיא, Amar Rav Ashi kegon Masa Machasya, דמפיק מכרך, demafik
mikrach, it was
it was smaller than a big metropolitan city, ומפיק מכפר, umafik mikfar,
but it's not a little village. Okay, תניא כוותיה דרב חסדא, Tanya
kevasei deRav Chisda, we taught like רב חסדא Rav Chisda that it
mattered about having rinsed the meat. הרי שהיה פתו אפויה וטבחיה טבוחה
ויינו מזוג ונתן מים אגבי בשר, Harei shehaya pasto afuya uzevachav tevuacha
veyeino mazug venatan mayim agabi basar, and the meat's been rinsed, ומת
אביו של חתן או אמה של כלה מכניסין את המת לחדר ואת
החתן ואת הכלה לחופה ובועל בעילת מצוה ופורש,
umes aviv shel choson
o imah shel kallah machnisin es ames lacheder ve'es hachoson ve'es hakallah
lachupah uvo'el beilas mitzvah uforesh, ונוהג שבעת ימי המשתה ואחר כך נוהג
שבעת ימי אבילות, venohag shivas yemei hamishteh ve'achar kach nohag shivas yemei
aveilus, וכל אותן הימים v'chol osan hayamim הוא ישן בין האנשים והיא
ישנה בין הנשים. hu yashein bein ha'anashim v'hi yesheinah bein hanashim. Okay,
so therefore until that was pretty much exactly identical except for the
fact that it was וטבחיה טבוחה. zevachav tevuacha. So let's take a
minute to talk about some of the points that we mentioned. First
of all, I want to say something about the circumstances of the
loss. You know nowadays, pretty much any postponement is a loss because
there goes my, what is it, $5,000, $10,000 deposit on the wedding
hall, right? So and it's also, it is a little fun, right?
Because of the phrase of that you'll have to lose the meat
and you'll have the fresh baked bread and you have the freshly
mixed wine, right? So that's a big financial loss. So then why
should it also require אביו של חתן או אמה של כלה? aviv
shel choson o imah shel kallah? Right? I mean there's a huge
financial loss. Isn't that enough? So even if the father is around
of the חתן choson to help him get ready a month from
now, it's still a huge financial loss. Do you need both factors,
both a huge financial loss and that the particular appropriate parent won't
be around? I don't know. You know that's funny, okay. And certainly
when this is applied contemporaneously, in contemporary cases, there are definitely פוסקים
poskim that are willing to be not so exact of אביו של
חתן, aviv shel choson, although the גמרא Gemara says ודוקא, vedavka, because
you know the real question is what's the context where there's like
a huge loss, you know in terms of what the significance will
be. Although you could say the גמרא Gemara really means it, that
if it's just a financial loss that's not enough. What it really
has to be is it has to be both the financial loss
and that it can't be replicated. But if it can be replicated
even though it's going to mean spending another $20,000, then okay, you
lose the $20,000. Of course, I say that I don't have the
$20,000 to spend, then it also can't be replicated. All right, so
that's just the circumstances under which we would allow this. Yes, Dov?
Is is the issue of the father of the חתן choson that
it's financial or that it's emotional and personal?
Yeah, it does not seem as much as financial as much as
more practical, like the father is going to be the one helping
you take care of all of the arrangements and overseeing it and
preparing it for you.
No one will do that with the same attention and exactly, exactly.
And right, and probably emotional aspect too, yes.
I would agree. Yes, David, can you lower that blind because it's
on one of your eyes, either David.
So yeah, tell me about this emotional aspect.
Whoa, whoa.
Okay, I guess oh, all right, that was a good hit. All
right, well, oh my gosh. All right,
everybody all right? All right. Moving on.
Oh my gosh. All
right, yeah. one night
and then get divorced. Right? That same questions about emotional aspects
are not
really addressed
too
much.
Yeah.
That
is true. That is true. Right, right, right. Although here that might
be I'm sorry if I'm at this thing I'm just trying to
get the... Yeah, although that might be although that might be a
little bit of what's going on why it's specifically, you know, אם
של חתן em shel chatan but because of that but you're right.
The גמרא Gemara is not explicit about the emotional. The גמרא Gemara
doesn't
always by principle ignore the emotional things or sometimes it very much
pays attention to it. So let yeah go ahead but I want
to go back and explicate. Let me go back and explicate some
of these issues, okay? So
so the question here is right what's the idea of postponing? Like
if an אונן onen is also so like is it okay to
do a חופה chuppah and have sex during אנינות aninus is that
better than doing it during אבילות? aveilus? So first of all there's
a debate whether sex is אסור assur for an אונן. onen. Number
one there's that's debated. So it might be and even if sex
is אסור assur for an אונן onen it's probably less seen as
like less אסור assur than it is for whatever that means but
like you know because it's debated presumably it's less serious than sex
for an אבל. avel. So that's number one why it might be
better you know to do it as an אונן. onen. Number one.
Number two is although some have a problem with that because אנינות
aninus like תוספות Tosfos if you take a look at a little
תוספות Tosfos here תוספות Tosfos says
where's the תוספות? Tosfos?
oh yeah the first תוספות Tosfos בביאת מצוה. Bo Bi'as Mitzvah. תוספות
Tosfos says like this the last line or last three lines והשתא
מקלינן טפי באנינות דאורייתא מאבילות דרבנן. v'hashta maklinan tfei b'aninus d'oraisa mi'b'aveilus
d'rabbanan. Right?
So by אנינות aninus which is a דאורייתא d'oraisa is generally assumed
that the first day although normally the דאורייתא d'oraisa aspect is for
קרבנות korbanot and not eating a קרבן korban but אנינות aninus at
least has a root in the תורה, Torah, okay, and therefore and
we're being more lenient to allow sex as an אונן onen from
אבילות aveilus which both mostly the practices of אבילות aveilus are seen
to be rabbinic. מידי דהוה נעילת הסנדל ועטיפת הראש וכפיית המיטה. Mi-di-d'hava
ne'ilas hasandal v'atipas harosh v'khifiyas hamitah. There are other aspects of אבילות
aveilus that don't apply to an אונן onen like wrapping the head
and not wearing shoes. So while אונן onen might be דאורייתא d'oraisa
and אבל avel דרבנן, d'rabbanan, okay, the status of an אונן onen
and the rules of an אונן onen are very different, like what
that status means and what the אבל avel status means. So that's
what תוספות Tosfos says like you know an אונן onen doesn't sit
on the ground doesn't rent his garments doesn't you know not wear
shoes and so on the status of an אונן onen is different.
So even when it comes to the issue of sex that might
not be אסור assur for an אונן onen or not אסור assur
the same degree, okay. So that's number one one of the benefits
of waiting to bury. Number two the other benefit benefit of waiting
to bury is that it allows for this is the real point
is that it allows for the חופה. chuppah. חופה chuppah is שמחה,
simcha, right? You can't have a חופה chuppah during אבילות, aveilus, right?
That's a major thing that's a חופה. chuppah. But an אונן onen
is not to the same degree although ironically whatever the status of
an אונן onen is he's not אסור assur in שמחה. simcha. Okay?
So therefore
so you know although it's true an אונן onen is אוכל בשר
ושותה יין okhel basar v'shoteh yayin so it's a funny type of
thing but the same sort of explicit איסור issur of שמחה simcha
I mean I don't think there're too many אוננים onenim that would
go about and look for those opportunities or whatever but again it's
not exactly the same as it is for an אבל avel the
status of אונן onen is different. So if the person was already
an אבל avel that would make it much more questionable. So that's
why we're going to do it as an אונן. onen. Of course
even if we're doing it as an אונן onen again once the
אבילות aveilus begins then even though you're already in the שבעת ימי
המשתה shevas yemei hamishteh there still is the איסור issur of sex
because it's דברים שבצנעה devarim shebetzin'a and that's why they have to
sleep separate. The final issue to address though is why it says
בביאת מצוה, Bo Bi'as Mitzvah, right? Why do they have to have
sex? Right? Why can't they just go ahead and have the חופה
chuppah and that allowed them to you know get started as it
were and have the wedding party etc. and they're going to have
to sleep apart anyway during the rest of the week, right? Why
דווקא davka בביאת מצוה? Bo Bi'as Mitzvah? So it could just be
you know you could look at it as two ways. You could
look at it as a basic as an allowance like we have
a little רחמנות rachmanus for them. Right? It's
not exactly a requirement but we have a little רחמנות rachmanus for
them you know they're they're all getting ready for their wedding and
then they're not going to be able you know we saw before
that if the woman is a נידה niddah the assumption is that
they wouldn't have the חופה chuppah when the woman is a נידה
niddah even if technically halachically it would be allowed. Obviously it's the
wedding night they're expecting to be sleeping together, right? So you could
sort of say it's like basically a type of like of a
רחמנות rachmanus for them, right? Or you could also say that since
again even though technically you can have נישואין nisuin without sex but
you know it underscores if the whole idea is to start the
status of שבעת ימי המשתה shevas yemei hamishteh and the status of
רגל regel and so on you know for the חתן וכלה chatan
v'kallah you want a little bit more make it real by them
actually having had sex not just like a pro forma wedding. Okay
because what we are actually doing is we're is we're is we're
creating that status of חתן וכלה chatan v'kallah to precede the status
of אבילות. aveilus. Okay, so again, the basic point is, why are
we postponing it? Okay, we're postponing it because if אבילות Aveilus would
begin, presumably sex, it would be harder to allow sex, even for
the one time, and it would be harder to allow the נישואין.
Nisuin. Both of those things ironically are easier to allow during the
אנינות. Aninus. Also by postponing it, it allows the שבעת ימי המשתה
Shiva Yemei HaMishteh to actually take effect, to precede. Okay, and that's
the real thing. If the אבילות, Aveilus, if you had the first
day of אבילות, Aveilus, then maybe we would allow you a one
minute wedding night, but we wouldn't allow you a שבעת ימי המשתה.
Shiva Yemei HaMishteh. Because here that took effect before the אבילות Aveilus
began, the status, that allows for the שבעת ימי המשתה Shiva Yemei
HaMishteh to precede and then the ניהוג Niyug of the אבילות Aveilus
to come next. That's point number one, why we manipulate it, because
again, it allows for the חופה, Chuppah, it allows for the sex,
it allows for the שבעת ימי המשתה Shiva Yemei HaMishteh to come
first. And number two, why are we saying that they have to
have sex? Maybe they don't have to. Maybe we're just having a
little רחמנות. Rachmanus. Or maybe that's done to really actualize, you know,
concretize the fact that we really are starting the wedding now and
the marriage now and that allows for the שבעת ימי המשתה Shiva
Yemei HaMishteh to come first.
Yes? But wait, one is if they're sleeping in company among, you
know, same genders, and doesn't that now become דבר שב... davar she-be...
not בצנעה b'tzina anymore? Because like now everyone knows, you know? So
like that's...
Yeah, it's a good point, that their way of avoiding having sex,
it starts by it's only private because then but who because who
knows, but the way you're taking care of it is making it
very public. It's an interesting question.
I don't know, it's a good point. Yeah. Another thing I see
from here is like, you know, sort of if you will, part
of my framing of this is like it's almost an obligation of
שבעת ימי המשתה, Shiva Yemei HaMishteh, because otherwise, you know, like let's
say they don't want to have it. Do they have to have
it? Like, you know, dad just died, whatever, I'm in no mood.
Right. You're saying like you really need to have this שבעת ימי
המשתה, Shiva Yemei HaMishteh, so is it like do
we learn from here that this is like a real thing you
have to do, even if you don't really feel like celebrating? Yeah,
I mean it's a good point. Yeah, I mean it's a status
of being during the week of שבעת ימי המשתה, Shiva Yemei HaMishteh,
so that status certainly obtains whether you're acting on it or not.
You know, our custom of having a meal every day of שבע
ברכות Sheva Brachos so we can do a שבע ברכות Sheva Brachos
for the whole week is a custom. The real הלכה Halacha is
that if you have a סעודה, Seudah, you make שבע ברכות. Sheva
Brachos. But but you're right. So it's not saying they have to,
but it's acknowledging the fact that that is the status of the
week. But so but you're right. No, it doesn't mean you have
to, but no, you're allowed to, that's your status and that's your
but yeah, it's a good point. One final question, Charlie, yeah.
Yeah, on the שבע ברכות Sheva Brachos thing, we didn't have שבע
ברכות Sheva Brachos except for the סעודה Seudah at the wedding.
But why, because it wasn't a first marriage?
It wasn't a first marriage for me and we were farmers.
Oh,
okay, so that's interesting. All right. Anyway, we'll get to that, we'll
get to שבע ברכות Sheva Brachos in a few days. Okay, one
final point to make about this, this big תוספות, Tosafos, because I
kept on sort of saying like could you do this if somebody
was already an אבל, Avel, right? And this actually comes up, that
you didn't have a special case where it was manipulated, they actually
did bury a relative a few days before, right? Can they go
ahead with the wedding? So maybe again, you wouldn't have נוהג שבעת
ימי אבילות, Noheg Shiva Yemei Aveilus, maybe we wouldn't have sex on
the wedding night, but do you have to suffer all of this
loss and can you go ahead with the wedding if the person
is actually an אבל? Avel? So that's what this big תוספות Tosafos
talks about and particularly he talks about it because the גמרא Gemara
says in two cases a person can get married right away: if
his wife dies and he doesn't have kids, so for the מצוה
Mitzvah of פרו ורבו, P'ru U'Rvu, and if the or not the
opposite, but his wife dies and he has very young kids and
he needs this you know and he needs to get married to
somebody to raise the kids. I mean obviously this is again a
very type of a society where that's only something that you know
you need the man would need a wife to do. So the
גמרא Gemara says get married immediately. So תוספות's Tosafos question is what
does immediately mean? Does immediately mean, right, within the week, during the
שבעה, Shiva, or does immediately mean after the שבעה Shiva but during
the שלשים? Shloshim? Okay, and that's the whole discussion that תוספות Tosafos
has, but תוספות Tosafos raises at least the possibility that in some
circumstances we would allow marriage during שבעה Shiva even when the אבילות
Aveilus already began. Okay, so this is the חידוש Chiddush of manipulating
it so the אבילות Aveilus hasn't begun, and what I've been trying
to point out is why it's more challenging when the אבילות Aveilus
has begun, but there are questions about when can we have the
wedding even when the אבילות Aveilus has begun. Okay, so now back
to the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, so that's the basic big חידוש Chiddush
of manipulating the whole thing. So now the גמרא Gemara says like
this: okay, the end of the ברייתא Braita which I stopped at:
וכן מי שפירסה אשתו נדה, Vechen mi shepirsah ishto niddah, about twelve
lines from the bottom. Somebody
whose wife became a נדה, Niddah, הוא ישן בין האנשים והיא ישנה
בין הנשים. Hu yashen bein ha-anashim ve-hi yashena bein ha-nashim. They have
to sleep separate. Now of course we know that's not true. I
mean, you know, the Falashas did that, right? When the woman was
a נדה, Niddah, you know, she slept in a separate
room like a, you know, ancient cultures that actually observe different types
of menstrual taboos often the women would sleep in a separate hut
in a separate hut. You know, the גמרא Gemara is very, very
clear that husband and... wife, you know, share a room when the
woman is a נדה. niddah. So what does this mean? So it's
assumed here, you know, very much by context to mean that the
woman became a נדה niddah before the couple has had sex on
the wedding night, okay, חופת נדה. chuppat niddah. So they have because
all of this is about what's happening on the חופה, chuppah, right?
This is all about the wedding night. The whole context is the
wedding night. So they haven't had sex yet. So if she's a
נדה niddah and they haven't had sex yet, then they don't have
already established a, you know, a sexual relationship. There's a lot of
urgency and then we're afraid that they won't be able to withstand
the temptation. And therefore we say they have to sleep in separate
rooms. This actually is a real הלכה. halacha. What do you do
by a חופת נדה? chuppat niddah? And how do you satisfy what
constitutes him with the men and her with the women in order
to address this? I'm not going to talk about that right now.
And so it'll be interesting you don't postpone the wedding but rather
you have it then.
You have the wedding but they sleep separate. But they didn't, you
already had the wedding. They go to the hotel room after the
wedding and she and she realizes she's a נדה. niddah.
So what wasn't the context of, you know, postponing the wedding?
That was the first case, that was the case of death. This,
yeah, this וכן מי שפירסה אשתו נדה, ve-chen mi she-pirsa ishto niddah,
his wife became a נדה niddah at the wedding on the wedding
night, הוא ישן בין האנשים והיא ישנה בין הנשים. hu yashen bein
ha-anashim ve-hi yeshena bein ha-nashim. וכן, ve-chen, I'm sorry, just read that.
I'm sorry, הוא ישן, hu yashen, no I'm sorry, okay, right. ואין
מונעין תכשיטין מן הכלה כל שלושים יום. ve-ein monin tachshitin min ha-kallah
kol shloshim yom. And now we're back to the sudden death that
occurred. So even though she's an אבלה, aveilah, she can put on,
you know, nice jewelry and beautify herself for during the שלושים shloshim
of the אבלות aveilus because it's their first month together. בין כך
ובין כך, bein kach u-vein kach, now regardless of whether you have
one of these special circumstances or not, okay, in a general case
of when a couple got married, so we're all talking about the
wedding night, that's like the heading of this, special cases about the
wedding night. Okay, so regardless of whether it's those cases, לא יבא,
lo yavo, you shouldn't have sex on the wedding night, לא בערב
שבת, lo be-erev shabbat, not ערב שבת erev shabbat means the wedding
was Friday, meaning not Friday night, okay,
ולא במוצאי שבת, ve-lo be-motzaei shabbat, and not Saturday night. Okay, it's
funny he called it ערב שבת, erev shabbat, okay. But anyway, not
Friday night and not and not Saturday night. So Friday night is
going to be an issue about breaking the hymen, you know, the
act of sex ruptures the hymen, is that like making a wound
and so on? Okay, we'll get to that. Why not Sunday is
not clear at all? Saturday night is not clear at all.
Now let's break now let's go back and analyze this. אמר מר:
amar mar: הוא ישן בין האנשים והיא ישנה בין הנשים.
hu
yashen bein
ha-anashim ve-hi yeshena bein ha-nashim. מסייע ליה לרבי יוחנן, mesayei lei le-Rabbi
Yochanan, this supports רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. דאמר רבי יוחנן: de-amar Rabbi
Yochanan: אף על פי שאמרו אין אבילות במועד, af al pi she-amru
ein aveilus ba-moed, although they said that there is אבלות aveilus doesn't
apply during the רגל regel and as we said like the שבעת
ימי המשתה shivat yemei ha-mishteh is like the רגל regel and that
took place first. So if it's like somebody was buried, you know,
buried during the רגל, regel, אבל דברים שבצנעה נוהג, aval devarim she-be-tzina
noheg,
but private matters, meaning not having sex, that's that's bare minimum of
what's includes in that, that applies. And that's why they have to
separate. So it's a very strong proof to רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan,
right? They got to separate. Otherwise, why couldn't they go on having
sex? Obviously that does apply even during the שבעת ימי המשתה. shivat
yemei ha-mishteh. Okay. דרש רב יוסף בריה דרב אמי משמיה דרבא: darash
Rav Yosef brei de-Rav Ami mi-shmei de-Rava: לא שנו אלא שלא בעל
אבל בעל אשתו ישנה עמו.
lo shanu ela
she-lo ba'al aval ba'al ishto yeshena imo. Now, this is only true
if they haven't had sex. Okay, but once they've had sex, then
they don't have to sleep separate.
But they do.
So the whole point is they just said they did have sex.
So the גמרא Gemara
says והא הכא דבבעל עסקינן? ve-ha hacha de-be-ba'al askinan? What are you
talking about? The whole point is that they have sex and then
they separate. דתני הוא ישן בין האנשים והיא ישנה בין הנשים. de-tani
hu yashen bein ha-anashim ve-hi yeshena bein ha-nashim.
No, הכי קאמר: hachi ka'amar: פירסה אשתו נדה. pirsa ishto niddah. No,
no, no, you misunderstood it. You were saying the first case they
had sex and then they separate. But when we say that she
became a נדה niddah the wedding night they have to sleep with,
you know, in separate rooms with, we know, with different, you know,
among men and among women, that's only if they never had sex.
But if they had sex on the wedding night and then she
became a נדה, niddah, then that's like just normally a wife having
sex, you know, wife having becoming a נדה niddah during the normal
course of marriage where they continue to sleep together. Okay, פירסה אשתו
נדה, pirsa ishto niddah, that this special הלכה halacha that husband and
wife have to be separate when she's a נדה niddah is only
when they've never had sex. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says והא
וכן תני? ve-ha ve-chen tani? But it says this is so so
is the הלכה halacha by נדה. niddah. So it sounds like the
same circumstances. So same circumstances would mean the same way by the
case about the death they have sex and then they sleep separate,
presumably by the נדה niddah as well they've already had sex. So
the גמרא Gemara says no, הכי קאמר: hachi ka'amar: וכן, ve-chen, no
it means the same הלכה halacha applies, it doesn't mean it's the
same circumstances. So it says וכן מי שפירסה אשתו נדה ולא בעל,
ve-chen mi she-pirsa ishto niddah ve-lo ba'al, in a case where the
woman became a נדה niddah on the wedding night and they never
had sex, in that case then the הלכות halachos are the same,
הוא ישן בין האנשים והיא ישנה בין הנשים. hu yashen bein ha-anashim
ve-hi yeshena bein ha-nashim. And as I said that is a real
הלכה halacha and it's a real challenging question about a case about
חופת נדה. chuppat niddah. This is why nobody wants to have a
חופת נדה, chuppat niddah, not just because they want to have sex
on the wedding night, because then you have to deal with these
הלכות halachos about how exactly do you arrange the sleeping arrangements. Okay,
I'm not going to tell you how I deal with that right
now. But anyway, yes.
So would it be getting back to the point even beforehand, would
this be grounds for moving up the wedding? Like you know she's
going to be a נדה niddah that day?
But you mean not doing it on a Wednesday? All right, possibly.
It's a good question. Within the גמרא Gemara that it was so
important to still do it on a Wednesday, that might very well
be. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, למימרא, l'meimra,
true, why couldn't it say אונס, oness, what if she became a
נדה? niddah? למימרא, l'meimra, well I guess you wouldn't have known or
what you would have known that וסת הקבוע. veset hakavuah. Yeah, but
that's not an אונס, oness, then plan in advance for that. Anyway,
moving on. All right, I don't know.
I got it. Moving on.
למימרא l'meimra דאבילות קילה ליה מנדה. d'aveilus kilei miniddah. Now the גמרא
Gemara understands, and this is going to be a strange גמרא Gemara
and the conclusion is going to be obvious. The גמרא Gemara understands,
why are the, in the first case, why are they sleeping separate
even after they've had sex? Because they're an אבל avel and an
אבל avel is not allowed to have sex. So the גמרא Gemara
understands bizarrely that that means that all אבלים, aveilim, anytime anybody's an
אבל, avel, husband or wife, they have to sleep separate. They have
to sleep הוא ישן בין האנשים והיא ישנה בין הנשים. hu yashen
bein ha-anashim v’hi yeshenah bein ha-nashim. I mean rather than understanding that
it's a special case because we did all this manipulation and they're
going to take it leniently, which is what the גמרא Gemara is
going to say at the end, it initially assumes that a normal
case of being an אבל avel or an אבילה, aveilah, they have
to sleep separate. So the גמרא Gemara says, why are we less
concerned that husband and wife will violate the איסור issur of נדה
niddah during the normal context of the marriage and we let them
share a room, and we're more concerned that they'll violate the איסור
issur of אבילות? aveilus? That's the way the גמרא Gemara understands. Obviously
we're going to reject that, but it seems that it thinks initially
that normal אבלים aveilim have to sleep... a normal case husband-wife אבל,
avel, they have to sleep separate. So the גמרא Gemara says למימרא,
l'meimra, this
suggests דאבילות קילה ליה מנדה, d'aveilus kilei miniddah, that they're more ready
to violate אבילות aveilus than נדה, niddah, and therefore we force them
to sleep separate in a normal case of אבילות, aveilus, the גמרא
Gemara is assuming, more than we do by a, you know, husband
and wife normally when she becomes a נדה. niddah. So the גמרא
Gemara says, is that really true? ואמר רבי יצחק בר חנינא אמר
רב הונא, v’amar Rabi Yitzchak bar Chanina amar Rav Huna, כל מלאכות
שהאשה עושה לבעלה נדה עושה לבעלה. kol melachot she-ha-ishah osah l’ba’alah niddah
osah l’ba’alah. All the types of domestic duties that a woman does
for her husband, right, it's going to be a whole פרק perek
later on about the domestic responsibilities of husband to of wife to
husband within a get a very particular type of a social reality.
So all of those duties
a נדה niddah can continue to do for her husband, right, she
can continue to sweep the house and cook the food and watch
the kids, חוץ, chutz, here's the only things that she can't do
when she's a נדה, niddah, חוץ ממזיגת הכוס והצעת המיטה והרחצת פניו
ידיו ורגליו, chutz mi-mezigat ha-kos v’hatza’at ha-mitah v’harchatzat panav yadav v’raglav, mixing
his glass, like making him drinks, you know, we would sort of
guess that would be contemporary application here means mixing the wine, but
that would be seen as a very intimate type of a thing,
let me make you a drink. Okay, ממזיגת הכוס והצעת המיטה, mi-mezigat
ha-kos v’hatza’at ha-mitah, laying the bed, which doesn't mean, תוספות Tosafot makes
a point of saying it does not mean doing the basic, you
know, spreading of the, you know, putting on the sheets and putting
on the blanket, but it means like putting on like the cover
on the top and smoothing it and making it all look like,
you know, pretty and nice, okay,
making the, whatever. Okay, making the bed. Yeah, but it's the end
part of the making of the bed. Okay,
והרחצת פניו ידיו ורגליו v’harchatzat panav yadav v’raglav and washing his hands,
feet, and face, which also is a very intimate experience that a
woman should not do as a נדה. niddah. So these are what
we're called הרחקות, harchakot, specific things of intimate acts that a wife
cannot do for a husband when she is a נדה. niddah. So
that's point number one, important for
הלכות נדה. hilchot niddah. ואילו גבי אבילות, v’ilu gabei aveilus, but when
it comes to a case by a woman being an אבילה, aveilah,
then or a man being an אבל, avel, תני ותני ברייתא, tani
v’tani braisa, אף על פי שאמרו אין אדם רשאי לכוף אשתו להיות
כוחלת להיות פוקסת, af al pi she-amru ein adam rashai lichof ishto
lihyot kochelet lihyot pokeset, even though when a woman is a נדה,
niddah, excuse me, an אבילה, aveilah, the husband cannot say, 'Hey, I
don't want you going around looking so, you know, disheveled, you know,
while you're an אבילה, aveilah, it doesn't make, you know, I want
to see my wife looking attractive.' He can't go ahead, he can't
do that. He can't go ahead and force her to put on
makeup, you know, and to put on, and to פוקסת pokeset might
mean to braid her hair. כוחלת kochelet is like to put makeup
on her eyes or רש״י Rashi might say rouge on the face.
It's a question what פוקסת pokeset means. Anyway, even though he can't
force her to beautify herself when she's an אבילה, aveilah, באמת אמרו,
be-emet amru, nevertheless, מוזגת לו את הכוס ומצעת לו את המיטה ומרחצת
לו פניו ידיו ורגליו, mozeget lo et ha-kos u-matza’at lo et ha-mitah
u-merachatzat lo panav yadav v’raglav, she still will do the the
she still does the wifely duties including the intimate wifely duties which
are, I mean not sex, but the ones that are the more
intimate in terms of the washing of the hands, feet, and the
face and the making of the drinks and so on. So the
upshot of this is you see that the הרחקות harchakot that apply
by a נדה, niddah, not doing these these these intimate acts, do
not apply by אבילות. aveilus. An אבילה, aveilah, woman's an אבילה aveilah
can do these intimate acts. So the הרחקות harchakot don't apply. So
you see that we're less concerned by אבילות, aveilus, we're less concerned
by אבילות. aveilus. Right. By the way, interesting question, which is which
the ראש Rosh discusses on the basis of this גמרא, Gemara, when
a woman or a man is an אבל avel or אבילה aveilah
and they're not allowed to have sex, do they have to sleep
in separate beds? Right? Do the הרחקות harchakot that we apply by
נדה niddah apply by אבילות? aveilus? This initial statement in the גמרא,
Gemara, so first I will say there's no גמרא Gemara that ever
says that. The גמרות Gemaros that say that discuss הרחקות harchakot by
נדה niddah never discuss it by things like תשעה באב, Tisha B'Av,
יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, or or אבילות, aveilus, which are the times
you're not allowed to have sex. It only discusses הרחקות harchakot by
נדה, niddah, and this particular case is explicit that some of the
most intimate הרחקות. harchakot. Are not a problem by an אבלה. avela.
That she's allowed to wash his hands, feet, and face, she's allowed
to make the drinks, and so on. Okay, so there's an interesting
question להלכה l'halacha about do they have to have separate beds, but
the simple sense one would get from this גמרא Gemara is no.
So the גמרא Gemara says look, אבלות avelus is even less of
a problem. So why therefore reading the earlier ברייתא braisa the way
it did, why would we demand that they be in different rooms?
Okay, it doesn't think yet that that ברייתא braisa is a special
case. It thinks it's a standard case of אבלות. avelus. So let's
see what the גמרא's Gemara answer is. So yes.
All right, so the גמרא Gemara says לא קשיא, lo kashya, it's
not difficult. כאן באבלות דידיה כאן באבלות דידה. kan b'avelus didei kan
b'avelus didah. Maybe it matters who's the אבל. avel. Is she the
אבלה avela or he's the אבל? avel? The גמרא Gemara assumes, right,
that the man is the one that is more not in control
of his sexual desires, of his lusts, and also can force sex
on the wife in a way that a woman can't force sex
on a man. So they're not force in the sense of like
rape, but like you know anyway be more, yeah whatever, right, be
more you know make people do things even if they don't really
want to.
So therefore it says
if he's the
אבל, avel, then we'll be more restrictive. Then we'll make them sleep
in separate rooms because he'll have like more of his יצר הרע
yetzer hara and he'll go ahead and he'll act on it and
we need to
make more safeguards. If she's the אבלה, avela, right, hold on let
me make sure I'm saying this right.
Yeah I'm saying it right. Okay, if she's the אבלה, avela, then
we're less concerned because since she's an אבלה avela even though you
know then she will somehow more like resist and you know be
less likely for him to be able to persuade her to have
sex with him if she's the actual אבלה. avela. So that's how
we sort of tried to reconcile it. That over there when do
we have them sleep separate? When he's the אבל. avel. Because when
he's the אבל avel he'll be more ready to violate his אבלות
avelus to have sex. Whereas if she's the אבלה, avela, what?
Except that he's an אבל.
avel. Right, I understand. Whereas if she's the אבלה avela even though
he wants to have sex she'll be able to resist him and
therefore we're less concerned. Okay. הא באבלות דידיה הא באבלות דידה. ha
b'avelus didei ha b'avelus didah. The גמרא Gemara says one minute, ואביו
של חתן או אמה של כלה קתני? v'avi she'choson o ima shel
kallah ktani? How can you say that? The case before was that
either his father died or her mother died. So it's both he's
an אבל avel and she's an אבלה avela and both of them
have them sleeping separate. So the גמרא Gemara says no, כי תניא
אשארא. ki tanya ashara. No, when it says either he's the אבל
avel or she's the אבלה avela that's for most all the other
הלכות. halachos. But for sleeping separate that would only be when he's
the אבל. avel. Okay so the גמרא Gemara says one minute. ומי
שאני בין אבלות דידיה לאבלות דידה? u'mi shani bein avelus didei l'avelus
didah? Since when do we make a distinction between who's the אבל
avel in terms of these concerns of sleeping separate and sex and
these types of issues? והתניא, v'ha tanya, we taught in a ברייתא.
braisa. מי שמת חמיו וחמותו, mi she'meis chamiv v'chamiso, if a man's
father-in-law or mother-in-law died. Okay his wife's parent, one of his wife's
parents. אינו יכול לכוף את אשתו להיות כוחלת להיות פוקסת. eino yakhol
lakhof es ishto liyos kokheles liyos pokeset. Again he can't say I
don't care you're an אבלה avela I want you to look pretty.
No, he cannot force her to beautify herself. אלא, ella, and not
only that, כופה מטתו ונוהג עמה אבלות. kofeh mitaso v'noheig imah avelus.
He has to upturn his own bed or couch, right which is
like we do this sort of as a covering of the mirrors
is our contemporary interpretation of this, but they would sort of do
this way of demonstrating that the house is sort of in אבלות
avelus by turning the beds upside down. So he would have to
turn his bed upside down and he would have to actually himself
respect אבלות avelus you know together with her. Observe well we'll get
to that in a minute. The גמרא Gemara will say that in
a minute. It hasn't said it yet. Okay but practice אבלות. avelus.
Okay so that's that. That's what it says when she's an
אבלה. avela. Okay. תניא באבלות דידיה, tanya b'avelus didei, הוא... I'm sorry
did I skip a line? וכן היא שמת חמיה או חמותה, and
similar she if her mother or father-in-law died or one of her
husband's parents, אינה משאה להיות כוחלת ולהיות פוקסת, eina mesha'ah liyos kokheles
v'liyos pokeset, she cannot beautify herself.
Now why not?
She's not an אבלה, avela, he's the אבל. avel. But that's because
what we're going to say at the end. That the spouse, no,
the spouse has to, presumably it's because the spouse has to respect
you
know the other spouse's אבלות avelus and he or she herself practice
some degree of אבלות avelus as well.
Even if he wants her to she can't.
Right but this is interesting, this is even when he's the אבל
avel and she's not, she cannot beautify herself, אלא כופה מטתה ונוהגת
עמו אבלות, ella kofeh mitasah v'noheig imah avelus, but she also turns
upside her bed and she also does a certain observance of אבלות
avelus as well in respect for the spouse, in respect for the
husband. So ואישתו... v'ishto... so גמרא Gemara says תניא באבלות דידיה הוא
ישן בין האנשים והיא תשן בין הנשים. tanya b'avelus didei hu yashein
bein ha'anashim v'hi tishon bein hanashim. Wait a minute. Wait
a minute hold on one minute let me just check one thing.
Right so that's the question right. So now's the question. The question
is it speaks about her being an אבל avel and him being
an אבל avel right, it speaks about those two scenarios and it
doesn't say by either of them that there's an idea of sleeping
separate. Here it tells you exactly it's dealing with the interaction of
husband and wife when one of them is an אבל avel and
it seems like neither when he's
an אבל. avel. In neither cases do they have to sleep separate.
So the גמרא'ס Gemara's answer is okay, write that line in, stick
that line into the ברייתא. Beraita. תני באבילות דבי. Tani be'aveilus d'vei.
So put it in, put it in to the ברייתא Beraita הוא
ישן בין האנשים ואשתו ישנה בין הנשים. hu yashen bein ha'anashim ve'ishto
yeshena bein hanashim. Fine. So put that into the ברייתא Beraita where
it says, you know, she turns up the bed and he turns
up the bed. It says a ברייתא Beraita also says, and by
the way, if he's an אבל, avel, he has to sleep in
a separate room, but not if she is. We're still going with
that answer. Don't worry, we're going to reject all of this. ה"ב
הכי קתני. Hav chin tanni. But one minute, it says the same
thing when he's an אבל, avel, when she's an אבילה. avela. No.
אהיכא דפחוס. ahicha d'pachus. No, that means
the same in terms of the putting on the makeup and the
beautifying, but there's still going to be a big difference of sleeping.
Okay, so we're going to completely rewrite the ברייתא Beraita in order
to maintain our answer of a difference when he's an אבל avel
and she's an אבילה.
avela. תני באבילות דבי Tani be'aveilus d'vei וכו'. v'chulu.
תני tani means let it say, amend the text, read this into
the ברייתא. Beraita. Okay, והא עמו קתני, veha imo katanni, but it
says she practices, she upturns her bed and observes אבילות avelus with
him. So if talking about bed and talking about being with him,
it sounds like they're sharing a bed. מאי לאו עמו במטה, mai
lav imo be'mita, doesn't it mean that they're sharing a bed? לא
עמו בבית. lo imo bevayit. No, no, no, it means when they're
in the same house she observes אבילות, avelus, but it's not getting
to the question of are they sleeping together or not.
Okay, כי הא דאמר ליה רב לחייא בריה, kide-amar lei Rav le-Chiya
breih, and this is what Michael's referring to, כי הא דאמר ליה
רב לחייא בריה, kide-amar lei Rav le-Chiya breih, like רב Rav said
to
חייא Chiya his son, באפה, be-apa, when
his wife was when his wife was sitting שבעה, shiva, באפה, be-apa,
when you're in your wife's presence, נוהג אבילותו, nohag aveluso, you should
also observe אבילות avelus out of respect to your spouse, ולא באפה,
ve-lo be-apa, if you're not in her presence, לא תנהג אבילותא, lo
tinhag aveluta, do not observe אבילות. avelus. So עמו, imo, when it
says observing אבילות avelus with him, doesn't mean sleeping in the same
bed with him; it means you observe אבילות avelus in his presence
out of respect. So what do we have right now? We basically
have that the גמרא Gemara understands that the sleeping separate that occurred
after this whole manipulation of the חופה chuppah and postponing the funeral
or whatever is really a general הלכה halakha that that an אבל,
avel, if one of the if the husband or wife is an
אבל, avel, they have to sleep in separate rooms. And that's much
more strict than נידה, niddah, right? נידה niddah they don't sleep in
separate rooms; that means general הרחקות harchakos that apply by נידה niddah
don't apply by אבילות. avelus. So why should we be so strict?
So right now the גמרא'ס Gemara's answer is it's when he's an
אבל avel and his יצר הרע yetzer hara gets the better of
him, and that's why, you know, when she's a נידה, niddah, she'll
say "I'm a נידה" niddah and she'll say no and he'll have
to respect that. If she's an אבילה, avela, she'll say "I'm an
אבילה" avela and you'll say no and she'll have to respect that.
But if he's the אבל, avel, we're assuming then he has to
be in a separate room because he can't control his יצר הרע.
yetzer hara. Okay, so now if we end the גמרא Gemara right
now, we'd say whenever a man is an אבל, avel, he has
to sleep in a separate room from his wife. Thankfully, we have
the next line of the גמרא. Gemara. So let's take a look.
The גמרא Gemara says לבתר הכי אמר רב אשי. levashay amar Rav
Ashi. רב אשי Rav Ashi says מי קמדמית, mi kamadmis, how do
you think you can compare
אבילות דהכא לאבילות דעלמא? avelus de-hacha le-avelus de-alma? This אבילות avelus to
a normal אבילות. avelus. A normal אבילות, avelus, of course, they don't
sleep in separate rooms, right? This is special.
אבילות דעלמא חמיר, avelus de-alma chamir, a normal אבילות avelus people treat
seriously, ולא אתו לזלזולי בה, velo asu lizilzuli bei, and they won't
treat it lightly and they won't disparage it, and as we said,
you don't even have to practice some the הרחקות harchakos by a
normal אבילות, avelus, okay, right, so the normal those intimate acts. But
אבילות דהכא, avelus de-hacha, this אבילות, avelus, כיון דאקילו בה רבנן, keivan
d'akilu rabbanan, since the רבנן Rabbanim were so lenient, אתו לזלזולי בה,
asu lizilzuli bei, he won't treat it seriously, and that's why we
have to go ahead and have them sleep separate. This one the
wedding, yeah, under the חופה. chuppah. מאי קולא, mai kula, what's the
leniency? אילימא דקתני בא ביאת מצוה ופורש, ileima de-katanni bo bi-vias mitzva
u-poresh, that they basically have sex before, you know, even though the
guy just died? So no, the גמרא Gemara says התם משום דלא
חלה עליה אבילות. hatam mishum de-lo chala alei avelus. That's not such
a leniency. You're allowed to have sex. So this גמרא Gemara makes
it sound like no problem with an אונן onen having sex, okay.
So the fact that, the fact that we
allowed sex when you were an אונן, onen, there's no איסור issur
of sex for an אונן. onen. Now actually there's a whole מחלוקת
machlokes if we פוסקן pasken there is an איסור, issur, but the
גמרא Gemara seems to assume not. So that wasn't the leniency. So
the גמרא Gemara says אילימא
התם משום דלא חלה אבילות. ileima hatam mishum de-lo chala avelus. אבילות
avelus hasn't begun. אי לרבי אליעזר עד שיצא מפתח הבית, ei l'Rabbi
Eliezer ad she-yeitzei mi-pesach habayit, that אבילות avelus doesn't begin either until
the corpse, the מת, meis, is removed from the house going towards
the funeral, going towards the cemetery קבורה. kevura. אי לרבי יהושע עד
שיסתם הגולל,
ei
l'Rabbi Yehoshua
ad she-yisamei ha-golel, or according to רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua until the
גולל golel is put down. The גולל golel means either according to
רש"י, Rashi, it means the, well, that's what תוספות Tosafos says, it's
the tombstone, but of course if you don't have a tombstone initially
רש"י Rashi says it means the, it means the cover of the
ארון, aron, the, you know,
the stone that covers the sarcophagus.
Yeah, well, or if not a sarcophagus, whatever. Anyway, right, but the
cover of the ארון, aron, the cover of the, you know, of
the coffin. So anyway, that's when אבילות avelus begins, either when he
leaves. When he's buried. So אבילות aveilus hasn't begun, so it's no
leniency having sex, presumably having sex as an אונן onen is not
a leniency. אלא דתני נוהג שבעת ימי המשתה ואחר כך נוהג שבעת
ימי אבילות. Ella detani noheg shivas yemei hamishteh ve'achar kach noheg shivas
yemei aveilus. The כולא kula is that we allow you to basically
manipulate it so that you can have your wedding, your week of
wedding before your week of the אבילות. aveilus. And that is the
כולא. kula. So not that we actually violated any הלכה. halacha. We
didn't violate any הלכה, halacha, but we manipulated the whole circumstance. And
one could add, by the way, it also sounds like there's fundamentally
no problem having נישואין nisuin during אנינות. aninus. That wasn't the כולא.
kula. נישואין nisuin wasn't or maybe it's, but the כולא kula is
that we manipulated everything to allow this to start first and the
אבילות aveilus to start later. And I would also add that אבילות
aveilus hasn't even really begun and the only thing that's kicked in
is דברים שבצנעא. devarim shebetzina. So in particular you would come to
treat the איסור issur of sex not seriously, right? Because number one,
you manipulated the whole thing so you didn't have to start being
an אבל. avel. You've already had sex. You're during the שבעת ימי
המשתה. shivas yemei hamishteh. The only aspect of אבילות aveilus that is
being נוהג noheg is the private איסור issur of not having sex.
So we can understand why you might not come to treat that
seriously. So that would make this a special case. Yes?
What did their beds look like? Not like ours.
No, no, no. The bed here means more like a couch. When
they say כפיית המיטה, kefiyas hamita, that probably more goes back to
the type... no, but that probably more goes back to the Tannaitic,
they probably more goes back to the Roman type of couch that
they would recline on to eat. I think it's more like...
they slept on this, that's what they slept on?
It sounds like כל מיטות שבבית. kol mitos shebabayis. It sounds like
more that's talking about the couches than it's talking about the beds
per se. I mean it includes the beds, but I think, anyway.
All right, something more to discuss when we get to מועד קטן,
Moed Katan, or actually we already did מועד קטן, Moed Katan, so
you'll have to wait another six and a half years or so
to get back. Okay, so we will end here.
Okay. What do you do about the shaving? I mean once you
shave you shave.